Welcome back to this tutorial. In this training we are going to be discussing about
troubleshooting common Microsoft Intune issues. If you are working as an IT system
administrator, managing client devices definitely you are going to encounter
issues. One of the advantage of Microsoft Intune is you can actually use Intune
at any given time to at least troubleshoot your devices and at least generate
reports to see which device have a specific issue. So for example if I go to my
dashboard, here on my dashboard first of all you can get a glance if there are
any issues with for example your compliancy device configuration or device
and romance you can see for example without device configuration it says policies
which error or conflict. So now we can decide to click on that and check which
of this device is giving which of the policies giving error. So we can see
this device with error. So here is the policy that I created the configuration
policy that I created, that's totally giving that error. So we can actually check
and see so it says you can see one is it the user principle name if I click on
that we can actually see a lot of so suited but here we can actually just go
down to see which of the error okay here we can see we have high high
privacy and false code integrity error. Well this totally feature machine so
probably it is possible to see such error. Well that shouldn't be any issue
because we can see a lot of so C-dead and just that hypervisor error message
here we go and enable visualization be security. So because this I'm using
the feature machine which I machine for this training purpose definitely
misses something like this. So if I go back again to all to my devices here on my
device you can see we have we can also see for example configuration policy
assignments failures we can see non-compliant devices so all devices are
currency compliance. Well I'll have just one device here so definitely I mean
I see that error but we can see with that we have one configuration policy
error message. So if I go to monitor here we can on a monitor you can see a lot
of reports we can totally check to see if there are any issues. For example we
can see it's device with restricted apps or we can see the driver of the
policies with a lot and romance failure I can't really click on that to see
refresh we see we don't have any error error meant failure at the moment. So
here we can tell you we can't tell you for example non-compliant devices we
can check if a device is not compliant so you're gonna get all the devices that are
not compliant and you kind of own a spot there as well. For example if I
scroll down again and check we don't have any autopilot devices policies with
non-compliant error devices we can also check on that and see you can see we
have one error device. And also sometimes we have issues whereby your device is
always specific device is not receiving a policy that has been deployed to
that device or to specific devices. So maybe a specific device is not receiving
that policy. What we got to do is do is to go to devices Windows device and on
another device we can click on another device and here for example I can say
sync. By clicking this sync it's going to what is going to happen it's going to
we are attempt to check in with this device. So if you're successful it will
sync code action. So if you deploy a policy to all your devices it takes time for
that policy to be deployed. Think some minutes about three or five minutes but if
you click sync it takes immediate effects for the policy to be deployed. So I
can click yes and the policy will be deployed and if no user is actually log on
to that device or if he uses log on to that device and you've informed that
user that well I'm going to restart your device you can tell a restart the
device from Intune. Why is it also go to restart a device from Intune or I've done
allowing the user to restart the device himself. But I restart the device from
Intune it gives you the ability to say well there is a connection between Intune
and other device. Because if I click for example I click restart I say yes. So it
says restart initiated and now if I go back again here we have that device so
let me go to the device. Here we have the device. Let me try to log on to
the device. So here we have the device and again this device because I've
actually initiate that restart reboot. So it will take some minutes and then
the initialization then I will see if we call from message the proper message which
says your device will restart in probably 60 seconds. So it's going to take some
time. One again the user will have all the opportunities which will close all
applications and devices on that device. So here we can see right now it says
your device administrator has scheduled a reboot you are about to be signed
out. So it means that the device is going to restart in no time. So mind you it
takes about maybe probably two to three minutes when you initiate the reboot
for the reboot to take effect. So I can click close. So by clicking close with
means that your device will restart in no time. So probably you want to make
sure that every single program that are open on that device is close to you. So
you will need to advise the user to close all programs open on that device. So
let's go back again to our Intune. And apart from that you can see this device
device action status. You see a restart pending, locate device pending,
collecting diagnostic complete. And also for example if I go to recovery key here
we can see the recovery key you can actually show the recovery key. We can see
the recovery key of this device because bitlocker has been configured on that
device using the Microsoft Intune as well. And again if I decided to just click
here close and then go back again to reports. Like we did I did a video on
reports on how to actually generate reports on Microsoft Intune for your
devices or for users or devices that are not compliance. You can see we have a
lot of reports we can't actually generate for our environment. So you can
generate reports for devices that are not compliance for device configuration
policies for Windows updates firewall Microsoft definite antivirals and even
endpoint analytic. So we can't really generate this all this reports. And again
if for example your device is having any issues you can't really troubleshoot
your device specifically by doing the following so let us with our device to
restart and then let me check you to my Windows 11 operating system to show
you where we can't really get some log files or not device. So let's go to our
Windows 10, our Windows 11 device and in our Windows 11 device let me maximize
this. So here we can't really go to file explorer. So in file explorer let's go
to this PC and then click on local drive. Here we have our program data. So if
you're not seeing this program data what you need to do is to go to view and
click sorry for that view then click show and you want to show the hidden
item. You can see it just disappear. So the hidden items are actually
programs that you don't want to delete from your device. So let's go to program
data and from program data let's go to Microsoft and here we need to go to let's
see we have the into management extension and then we have our log file. You
can see we have a lot of log if I for example up workload. So you can't really
see for example check inside. So this we actually give you a kind of idea if
something is wrong with your device you can't really client's health you can't
really check if you have any red error message showing here for you to be
able to check and verify what the problem is with your device we can also see
how the health script and the wind that it to up in victory. So I totally click
on that as well and check if we have any error message. You can see some yellow
warning message but for the rest don't have any red error message. And also you
know I've already configured a group policy to automatically register my
device in Intune. Sometimes you're admin the administrator will configure a
policy. They must be some devices which are not enrolling in Intune. So I want to
give you a specific tip. You know I've seen this in the past when you try to
enroll a device or you log on to that device with a specific user name. Mind
you that user must have the Microsoft Intune license which means the user
must have a license that allows him or how to use Microsoft Intune if not the
device may not get ready starting Intune. It may be on hybrid device which
of course the device is ready starting active in Azure Active Directory but
not in Intune. So you'll be seeing it in Azure Active Directory but you
definitely don't see that device in Intune. It will just show manage then it will
not be Intune or MD and the mobile device management. And one of that thing you
want to do again is the following. If for example we go to I'm going to search
for the company portal. Let's see we have the portal let's see. Okay I'm not
installing the company portal on this device yet but if for example we will have
issues or you want to actually download and install the company portal on this
device you need to go to the Microsoft store. Here we can just type for
example I can just enter and just type the company portal. Here we go you can
see we have the company portal up and then we can now click on it and then click
get to install it. Remind you when you download it and it's got to install a
device you still need to register your you still need to actually register your
accounts because you are again your account should have the Microsoft Intune
license. If not it is not going to work. Here we go you can see this is the
company portal. It's still so I can just click open to open it and then we can
start the installation. We can start the configuration process of the company
portal. So sometimes it means you want to use kind of a single sign-on to
configure your company portal if you were designing to the device using that
account. So let just hold on for this to get configured. You can see that every
configuration I made from the Intune portal is being configured you can
hit the green background and also the care of globalicity and it's using a kind
of a single sign-on to configure everything for me without me doing any other
configuration. For example we can decide to go to app what is going to take
some time for the other app that has been deployed to be listed here. So I
just wait for this and see what we got. So if I check apps that is where you can
see there is no apps because I've not deployed any apps to my environment. So
here we can have we can just click the download updates download and updates. You
can see there are no updates available. But sometimes updates have already been
pushed to this device with me take some time for the updates to be available or
if new updates are available they are going to be displayed here. Because if I
go to updates let me just go to updates check for updates. You can see at this
moment it says windows update settings are managed by organization. So you
can't check for updates because it has already been blocked that every update
will be download or update available will be actually pushed through Microsoft
Intune and not from not downloading it direct from the Internet from my
Microsoft website through the device. You see this here by this moment I know
updates are available and if I click device here we can see the device. So we're
also good to have and support we can also upload logs request help for the
pro level you guys press in the company portal we send logs to Microsoft what
is one of the just the laws that we send to Microsoft and sometimes for the
IT help desk you can get some valuable information here available which of
course you can send that information. You can call the IT help desk can sell an
email to your IT help desk to help you resolve some issues.